<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[jlaine.net]]></title>
  <link href="http://jlaine.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jlaine.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-05T10:54:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jlaine.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jarkko Laine]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project 4.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2014/01/21/project-45/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-21T12:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2014/01/21/project-45</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall – on the brink of transferring to the masters series in sports – I started a new <a href="http://projekti45.jlaine.net">triathlon project</a>. I’ve been looking for something new for a while and this seemed like a good opportunity to take it into action. I’ve also always loved triathlon. I’m a bit of a generalist in everything and always looking for variety<sup id="fnref:entrepreneur"><a href="#fn:entrepreneur" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> in everything I do.</p>

<p>The big problem in triathlon for me was that I was (and to an extent still am) a terrible swimmer. Sure, I can get by but if I tried to swim a longer distance, I quickly went out of breath, which is disturbing for someone with presumably great oxygen intake. I assume that’s very common for quite a few tri-newbs, so I also wanted to document the process as it goes.</p>

<p>Writing a sport project blog is what everyone seems to be doing right now, so I wanted to do it with a twist. I have no illusions that very many people are actually interested in me or how I’m doing. Thus I’m always trying to write articles with the audience in mind: people who have a background in endurance sports but have not done (or have recently started) triathlon.</p>

<p>For now I’m doing it in Finnish. But who knows, if the interest is there, I might start translating the articles in English as well. So, if the language isn’t an issue, come on <a href="http://projekti45.jlaine.net">over</a>.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:entrepreneur">
      <p>That’s probably why I’m a software entrepreneur rather than a pure developer. I get bored quickly when I do just one thing for too long – be it coding, designing or marketing.<a href="#fnref:entrepreneur" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open letter to specialty coffee roasters]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2013/09/26/dear-specialty-coffee-roaster/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T12:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2013/09/26/dear-specialty-coffee-roaster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="dear-specialty-coffee-roaster">Dear specialty coffee roaster,</h2>

<p>Let me start by saying that I love you, each and every one of you. I love what you’re doing and respect the work you’re doing to bring better coffee to us all and fight the apathy of people sinking in them chain-oil-like substance just to get a fix of caffeine.</p>

<p>That said, it’s time for some tough love. Tough in the sense that I’m going to be quite outspoken and love in the sense that it’s all for the common good of you and me. So here we go.</p>

<p>Here’s the problem with your coffee: <em>It’s sold stale</em>. Why? Because you set the expiry date to something ridiculous like 3 months or (gasp!) a year. And retailers <em>will</em> sell it until that date and not order fresh coffee until they nearly run out of the previous batch. They will do this because it’s more economical for them and <em>it’s not their coffee that’s sold and their reputation that’s on the line</em>. Thus, your coffee is sold stale. And you don’t want that.</p>

<p>But, you say, every coffee in the supermarket is sold with an expiry date of up to a year in the future. So what? You’re not in the specialty coffee business to be just like everyone else. First of all, their coffee is probably stale in any case since it’s sold pre-ground, which makes it go bad in a matter of days. And secondly, their coffee is of so bad quality in the first place that who the fuck cares whether it’s stale or not when used?</p>

<p>Your coffee can be the most awesome single-origin bean in the history of micro-roasting, but when it’s used four months after roasting, it will be stale. And it will be sold until the very last day, because it’s a niche product with fairly low turnover.</p>

<p>Maybe your argument is that most buyers will never notice. That gets us to the heart of the problem. <em>You will want them to notice</em>. You want them to become coffee conoisseurs if they aren’t already. Because if they don’t notice the difference, they shouldn’t be your target market in the first place.</p>

<p>Here’s a little Marketing 101 to you: you want to target a niche. In your case, the niche should probably be the people who really care about the taste and quality of their coffee. Like said above, most people will probably not notice the difference between your Kiawamururu AA and the generic supermarket blend destroyed with robusta. Their taste buds are long since burned. And of those who <em>can</em> taste the difference, most just don’t care enough to justify the significant price difference and inconvenience of sourcing and self-grinding specialty coffee. Trying to convert them is a one-way street of frustration ending up in a bankruptcy.</p>

<p>You are, by definition, a small fish. Trying to target everyone is as good as targeting no one. It will cost you a fortune and be much less effective in actually finding your ideal customers. And this is just from the marketing standpoint. An even more important point to make here is that by making it not only possible but very likely to make your coffee available as stale, you are alienating the very core of the niche market you should be aiming at – the people who not only buy your expensive coffee, but the ones who talk, nay, <em>rave</em>, about it; the ones who serve it to their friends and perhaps <em>convert them as well</em> into your customers and evangelists.</p>

<p>Here’s the thing that I’m quite sure you know: good, fresh coffee is freshware, sold to a small subset of coffee drinkers. Don’t pretend it’s something else. Don’t be like the one-person consultancies talking in enterprise-y terms and about “we” instead of “I”, destroying their personality in the process. Milk producers don’t set the expiry dates of their produce to several months in the future just to get retailers to sell every one of the cartons because (regulations aside) they don’t want their milk to be sold sour. You don’t want your coffee to be sold stale, either. So do something about it. There is no reason in the world for not to do the same as <a href="http://shop.squaremilecoffee.com">Square Mile</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Brew within one month of roasting.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Could you please do the same? For me, and in the end, for you.</p>

<p>XOXO,</p>

<p>//jarkko</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let your data tell a story]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2013/09/23/let-your-data-tell-a-story/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-23T09:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2013/09/23/let-your-data-tell-a-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you missed it, I just <a href="http://bearmetal.eu/theden/let-your-data-tell-a-story/">wrote a long write-up of my Monitorama.EU talk in the Bear Metal blog</a>. If you’re working on big data, design, or visualizations, you probably want to read it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It’s not about us, it’s about you (and not really about you, either)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2013/08/29/not-about-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-29T09:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2013/08/29/not-about-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The common perception is that sales and marketing is mostly about telling how good you or your product are. That it’s all about me, me, me. Us, us, us. I tend to disagree. People don’t really care about you, they care about themselves. And while that sounds selfish, it really isn’t, it’s just a natural fact of life. Why should they really care about you?</p>

<p>So to be successful both in creating products and services and marketing them you have to step in your customers’ shoes. How can make <em>them</em> kick ass? That’s the driving force behind <a href="http://bearmetal.eu/">Bear Metal</a>, so I kicked off the company blog with an <a href="http://bearmetal.eu/theden/its-not-about-us-its-about-you/">article</a> that isn’t the traditional “who we are” post but a dive into the philosophy mentioned above.</p>

<p><a href="http://bearmetal.eu/theden/its-not-about-us-its-about-you/">Read the full story at The Den</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Runemployed]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2013/07/01/runemployed/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-01T20:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2013/07/01/runemployed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago, <a href="http://objo.com/2013/01/31/funemployment/">several</a> <a href="http://benscofield.com/on-taking-time-to-think/">friends</a> announced taking a few steps back from their hectic work life, taking perhaps on some freelance clients but mostly enjoying life, family, getting into shape, or whatever they felt they had been neglecting in their busy lives as software professionals and entrepreneurs. The term they often used for this was <em><a href="http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-funemployment4-2009jun04,0,7581684.story">funemployment</a></em>.</p>

<p>June 30th was my last day doing full-time contracting for <a href="http://wildfireapp.com">Wildfire</a>. I joined the company back in 2008 when the company was basically the co-founders, Victoria and Alain, and a couple of remote contractors. During the past five years I was fortunate enough to see a bootstrapped startup grow to a juggernaut of hundreds of employees and eventually a <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/07/31/google-acquires-wildfire/">lucrative acquisition target</a>.</p>

<p>In many ways I always experienced Wildfire as my own product even though that technically never was the case. There’s just something in midwifing a product, seeing its first paying customers, then the first thousand (including several Fortune 50 companies), and so on. That’s a lesson money just cannot buy.</p>

<p>The folks at Wildfire were always awesome to us contractors. We were allowed to work pretty much how much we wanted, wherever we wanted. That might have been just as well from the fells of Lapland as from a B&amp;B <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/5137528302/in/set-72157613678662906/">somewhere in New Zealand’s South Island</a>. That trust and philosophy also let and motivated us to deliver.</p>

<p>There are some things I missed during the past few years, however. Being wholly subsumed by Wildfire meant that I all but gave up writing and making serious contributions to open source projects. That’s something I want to change.</p>

<h2 id="say-hello-to-bear-metal">Say hello to Bear Metal</h2>

<p>Working with <a href="https://twitter.com/erkkie">Erkki</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tarmo">Tarmo</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/methodmissing">Lourens</a> for several years built a special bond between us. A 100 % trust in everyone pulling their weight is surprisingly quite a luxury these days. Thus, while our work on Wildfire will soon be done, our work together will not. We’re not burned out enough to look for funemployment. We love what we do. However, one thing we love the most is doing it wherever we want to be, be it hitting the XC tracks of Äkäslompolo, wakeparks (with the bidirectional cable) of Bangkok or trail-marathoning across islands mid-Atlantic. I’d like to call that <em>runemployment</em>.</p>

<p>That’s something we’re not willing to give up. Because of that shared passion and mutual trust we decided to set up a shop of our own, by the four us. We’re called <a href="http://bearmetal.eu">Bear Metal</a> and we’re open for business beginning next fall. We’re a cross-functional team ready to build web businesses from scratch and also provide training and consulting services about building and running large-scale Ruby apps; deploying them with Chef; and <a href="http://www.zeromq.org/intro:commercial-support">ZeroMQ</a>.</p>

<p>Come join us in our run into the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to get started with bootstrapping]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2013/05/13/how-to-get-started-with-bootstrapping/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2013/05/13/how-to-get-started-with-bootstrapping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="bootstrapping-resources">Bootstrapping Resources</h2>

<p>In the <a href="http://2013.scottishrubyconference.com">Scottish Ruby Conference</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/tekin">Tekin Suleiman</a> gave a great talk about his experiences in bootstrapping a web app. At the end of the talk there was a question about further resources into the subject. I’ve been into this thing for years now (both in the form of building <a href="http://www.wildfire.com">Wildfire</a>, dribbling with personal projects, and now with <a href="http://bearmetal.eu">Bear Metal</a>), so here’s my take on the subject.</p>

<p>First things first: Tekin mentioned Amy Hoy’s <a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/30x500-is-dead-long-live-30x500">30x500 class</a> and that has been my philosophical home in the field as well. I was fortunate enough to join the class early on, but even after several price hikes it’s worth many times its cost if you’re committed to bootstrapping. But you <em>really, really</em> need to be committed. If not (yet), you should still read her blog <a href="http://unicornfree.com">Unicornfree</a> from top to bottom to gain lots of insight into all things bootstrapping.</p>

<p>Another commonly mentioned resource is the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0307887898/?tag=jlainenet-20">Lean Startup</a> book by Eric Ries and the lean startup community sparked by it. My issue with the book for a bootstrapper is that in the end of the day, its ideology is still your normal startup mentality, only executed in a more nimble manner. That said, it might be worthwhile to read the book, if only to know what people are talking about when they mention the MVP or validated learning.</p>

<p>If you’re doing anything related to web, Patrick McKenzie’s blog <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/blog/">Kalzumeus</a> and the related podcast is an indispensable resource. Another one is Brennan Dunn’s <a href="http://planscope.io/blog/">blog</a> and mailing list. <a href="http://nathanbarry.com">Nathan Barry</a> has also written a lot of good stuff on the topic recently.</p>

<p>If you’re a conference kind of person, there are a few that hit the soft spot quite nicely. Hoy organizes one called <a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/baconbizconf-philadelphia-may-30-31">BaconBizConf</a> in late May. <a href="http://www.microconf.com">Microconf</a> (unfortunately this year’s conf already was in April) is another one that has received a lot of praise. <a href="http://lessconf.lesseverything.com">LessConf</a> was great as well from what I’ve heard but I believe the past one was the last one there was.</p>

<p>Random resource pointers aside, I’ll next delve into some (as random) details and lessons I’ve learned about bootstrapping.</p>

<h2 id="perils-of-starting-with-an-idea">Perils of starting with an idea</h2>

<p>An old adage says that ideas are worth nothing, execution is everything. However, most people will only hang on to the latter part of the saying, not taking the first part literally. In her class, Hoy takes this one step further, explaining why starting by looking for an idea to build is actually harmful for you. The reasons for this are manifold.</p>

<p>First of all, it is not very likely that you have a unique, great idea that is also sellable. It is much more likely that someone already had the same idea, tested it, and <em>found out it did not work</em>. Second, thinking that the starting point of a company is an idea found in a flash of deitic brilliance is a very nice path to despair. This effect Hoy calls the idea quicksand. In it you think you find a great idea, sit on it, let it subsume you, and finally give up. It victimizes and paralyzes you.</p>

<p>Lastly, starting a company with an idea is very likely to cause your thinking to suffer from serious <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias">confirmation bias</a>. You harvest information that supports your idea and dismerit or ignore cues that would tell you your idea is in reality a stinking, unsellable pile of yak poo. We all are affected by it and it’s really, really hard to avoid it. So do yourself a favor and don’t start bootstrapping with a ready-baked idea.</p>

<h2 id="so-what-should-i-start-with-then">So what <em>should</em> I start with, then?</h2>

<p>To sell anything, you need a market. You need an audience. An audience is a mostly homogenous group of people. Ruby developers. Web designers. Freelancers. <em>Bootstrappers</em>. You don’t necessarily have to be a part of the audience yourself, although that does help you both in finding the pains and later when you’re actually building your product because of your domain knowledge.</p>

<p>Once you have picked an audience, you can start finding out what really bugs that audience. Lurk in their forums, and spy on them for insight. What itches do they have, from which colossal pains do they suffer? <em>This</em> will form the basis for the business you’ll build.</p>

<p>Don’t directly ask whether they’d need this and that. Actually search for patterns and keywords in how they describe issues they’re having. This is what Hoy calls a Sales Safari.</p>

<h2 id="content-marketing">Content marketing</h2>

<p>One topic that pops up in almost every discussion about marketing effectively on the web is content marketing. What it basically means is that by providing valuable content to your audience you teach them and simultaneously build trust in yourself. This appoints you as an authority in the field.</p>

<p>An important thing to note is that you do <em>not</em> have to be a super expert in the field in question, just a notch above the knowledge level of your audience. This means you’re actually more likely to remember the pain and issues you encountered when you were in the same situation. For a seasoned expert this might be years in the past and thus something only vaguely in their minds. Thus it is easy for them to take many of the issues as given.</p>

<p>What you <em>do</em> have to be good at, though, is writing. If you have a big budget you can hire people to do it, but for a bootstrapped company at least one of the insiders needs to be a wordsmith. Sorry to break the bad news but there just isn’t a way around it. As said many times over, <em>if you can’t write clearly, you can’t think clearly</em>.</p>

<p>By writing skills I don’t mean writing grammatically perfect English (or whatever language you use to reach your audience). Grammar is important for sure, but much more important is communicating your ideas effectively. The most important thing to learn the ropes here is practice, but here are some resources you might want to have a look at for getting better at writing.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0060891548/?tag=jlainenet-20">On Writing Well</a> is a great general guide on writing effective prose.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0452272955/?tag=jlainenet-20">Writing for Story</a> by the two-time Pulitzer prize winner Jon Franklin is a succinct introduction to writing gripping narrative in non-fiction. Storytelling is one of the most powerful techniques we have to grip our audience and get our ideas through.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0887232981/?tag=jlainenet-20">Breakthrough Advertising</a> is a bible for writing effective ad copy. While you might never become a copywriter, your goals are very much the same. Unfortunately the book is out of print and very hard to get your hands on. You <em>might</em> (I’ve been told) find the full text from the net, though, using your favorite search engine.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.copyblogger.com/blog/">Copyblogger</a> (subscribe to their RSS feed or mailing list) is a blog about pretty much all of the above. The amount of new content there is a bit on the high side but the quality makes up for that.</li>
</ul>

<p>Once you got the basics covered, you’re ready to get into the nitty-gritty details of teaching your audience. Neil Patel of Crazy Egg and Kissmetrics just recently published a free minibook called the <a href="http://www.quicksprout.com/2013/04/29/the-advanced-guide-to-content-marketing/">Advanced Guide to Content Marketing</a>. Aforementioned Copyblogger also has a <a href="http://www.copyblogger.com/content-marketing">series of articles about content marketing</a>. One thing that invariably exists in these primers is building a warm email mailing list.</p>

<h3 id="the-power-of-email">The Power of Email</h3>

<p>As a geek it might be easy to dismiss email as a communication method as old-fashioned and something people mostly ignore. I mean, everyone prefers to get their daily RSS fix or (nowadays) read about your stuff on Twitter. Nothing could be further from the truth. Growing a list of email newsletter subscribers is by far the most effective method of reaching your audience. There are a couple of reasons for this. Firstly, it is way more personal. Most email list software lets you personalize your emails (so do collect at least the first name of your audience members, if only as an optional field), and if you write them in a conversational tone, the reader will react to them in a completely different manner than to a more generic form such as a blog post.</p>

<p>Secondly, in the spirit of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permission_marketing">permission marketing</a>, everyone subscribed to your list has already given you permission to penetrate their email inbox. This is A Good Thing<sup>TM</sup>. You’re given a lot of trust. Just remember not to fail that trust. Always think how what you’ll write will benefit and teach the readers. If your newsletter is literally a collection of news about <em>you, you, you</em>, your readership will disappear faster than you can say MailChimp.</p>

<p>So, here were some random pointers for getting started with bootstrapping. Obviously, it’s a life-long path so taking up everything at once is pretty much a doomed undertaking (I’ve been taking Amy’s course at least three times already). So give yourself time, but <em>get started now</em>. And ferchrissake, don’t try to sell anything to consumers. Why? That’s a topic for another post.</p>

<p>Did I miss something? Anything else you’d like to read about bootstrapping? <a href="https://www.twitter.com/jarkko">Drop me a note</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scaling your Frontend &ndash; Graphics in the Era of Retina Screens]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2012/11/10/scaling-your-frontend-graphics-in-the-era-of-retina-screens/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2012/11/10/scaling-your-frontend-graphics-in-the-era-of-retina-screens</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s my deck from the Tampere Web Dev meetup on the 10th of November, 2012.</p>
<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="f2dd78000d670130372a1231381d9beb" data-ratio="1.37081659973226" src="http://jlaine.net//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script><p>Thanks to Thomas Fuchs for <a href="http://retinafy.me">retinafy.me</a> and <a href="http://www.fngtps.com/2012/reasonable-ways-to-use-high-resolution-images-on-retina-displays/">Thijs van der Vossen</a>.</p>
<p>If you enjoyed the talk, you might consider signing up for my up-and-coming eBook, <a href="http://forgottensvg.com">Forgotten <span class="caps">SVG</span></a>.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Great Coffee]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2012/01/16/introduction-to-great-coffee/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2012/01/16/introduction-to-great-coffee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a talk I gave in the first Tampere Web Dev meetup in January 2012</em>.</p>

<script src="http://speakerdeck.com/embed/4f11d91ed28ef6001f010f3e.js"></script>

<p>I don’t have a very long history with coffee. To be honest, I really only started drinking it when I was well into my twenties. Even then, I didn’t really like it, but surviving through exam periods took the better of me. It wasn’t until 2010 – when I first heard about Aeropress and then stumbled upon <a href="http://www.paperplanes.de/">Mathias Meyer</a> – that I found out there is a whole another world of coffee I had never before explored. Thus, with the enthusiasm of a beginner and the confidence of a 20-year-old, I shall tell you about my journey.</p>

<p>I won’t go into too much detail or technicalities. This will just be an introduction with the bare minimum you’ll need to get started. There are limitless opportunities for experimenting in the world of coffee. Now is not the time for that.</p>

<p>This will be a very opinionated piece. Many people – even coffeelovers – would disagree with many points. They would be be wrong, of course, but still have a right to their opinions.</p>

<p>Let’s start by defining what makes good coffee. Actually, let’s flip the question around and talk about what does <em>not</em> mean good coffee.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>If you think you need milk or sugar in your coffee, you’re not talking about good coffee. Sorry, but you just aren’t. Even with good coffee you might <em>choose</em> to use them – I will frown upon it, but hey, it’s your choice – but you won’t <em>need</em> them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Espresso (necessarily).</strong> Many people I know say that they don’t like any of those fancy coffees, by which they mean that they don’t like espresso. To be honest, I don’t care that much for espresso, either. I like good espresso like the next guy, but I actually think that great filter coffee beats the hell out of good espresso any day.</p>

    <p>The difference is a bit like between a vodka shot and an exquisite old Scotch. Sure, you can make great drinks from the vodka, too, but it’ll never be as smooth as a dram of 25-year-old Bowmore.</p>

    <p>The bottom line in my opinion is that while you might want to delve into espresso geekery later on, it’s not the best place to start. Because great coffee shouldn’t be…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Prohibitively expensive.</strong> Since we don’t start our love affair with coffee with Espresso, we also don’t need equipment that sets us back hundreds or even thousands of Euros and is a hassle to maintain. To me, starting the hobby should be reasonably inexpensive and have a gentle enough learning curve.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>With that in mind, let’s find out how to get the most out of your coffee experience. The founder of <a href="http://www.hasbean.co.uk">Has Bean Coffee</a>, Stephen Leighton, says the secret to the very best coffee is “fresh”, “fresh” and “fresh”. Just to make sure, I’ll throw another “fresh” in the mix myself.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Fresh Beans</strong>    Coffee is freshware. I’ll paraphrase a diagram from <a href="http://www.websitefolder.net/wendelboe/art-2.asp?id=24&amp;iPageID=5">Tim Wendelboe’s book</a> here:</p>

    <div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://skitch.com/jarkko/g3npf/img-0071"><img src="https://img.skitch.com/20120116-bhwhs1gjq9rne95248nbcxcnj3.preview.jpg" alt="IMG_0071" /></a><br /></div>

    <p>Freshly roasted coffee beans take a couple of days to settle to their best form. After that, they remain optimal for a few weeks. After about four weeks – and sooner if they are in contact with oxygen, i.e. you opened the bag – they start going stale fairly rapidly.</p>

    <p>This brings us to a measurement of roaster honesty. I’ll start with the best example, Square Mile Coffee:</p>

    <div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://skitch.com/jarkko/g3npc/img-1189"><img src="https://img.skitch.com/20120116-q6p5e53t1q97nfm9j8egbk647w.preview.jpg" alt="IMG_1189" /></a></div>

    <p>“Brew within one month of roasting”</p>

    <p>As you can see, this pretty much matches with Wendelboe’s graphic.</p>

    <p>The next level is Has Bean. They tell the coffee is best within one month, but you should definitively use it within three.</p>

    <p>Down another notch, we have Kaffiino.</p>

    <div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://skitch.com/jarkko/g3npt/img-1193"><img src="https://img.skitch.com/20120116-1i2mh47g35ntjrw318qaicyjq4.preview.jpg" alt="IMG_1193" /></a></div>

    <p>They still mention the roasting date, but pretend the coffee is still good half a year after roasting. It isn’t.</p>

    <p>On the bottom level we have most of the commodity coffees. They tend to give anything up to year before the expiry date. What’s worst, <em>they do not tell the exact roasting date</em>, so you’re left with guessing how much time they give their coffee to go stale and calculating from there when it was roasted. This is pure dishonesty. The roasting date is <em>the</em> most important thing on the label of a coffee bag. Unfortunately, even many reasonably good specialty coffee roasters (like Johan &amp; Nyström and at least sometimes, Mokkamestarit) can be found on this pathetic level.</p>

    <p>The lesson to learn here: <em>buy only from roasters that can guarantee the freshness of the roast</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Fresh Grind</strong></p>

    <p>Note that in the previous point, I only talked about fresh <em>beans</em>. That’s because <em>you should never buy your coffee pre-ground</em>. For commodity coffee, it doesn’t really matter whether they give you six or twelve months before the expiry date because <em>the grinds sold to you are already stale when they hit the selves</em>.</p>

    <p>The issues with pre-ground coffee are manifold. First, grinding coffee releases a large part of its aroma, which are lost forever if you don’t use the grinds immediately. Second, coffee really hates oxygen, which should be clear to you by now. When the coffee is ground, there is much more surface that’s exposed to the damned gas than with beans. Lastly, different brewing methods call for different grind levels. Good luck trying to make a good French press with coffee that’s ground to Aeropress level without drowning in sediment.</p>

    <p>So, the lesson #2: <em>Buy your beans whole and buy your own grinder</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Fresh Water</strong></p>

    <p>To be honest, I don’t think this is as much of an issue in Finland, where most of the tap water is pretty good. Sure, some conoisseurs want to buy bottled spring water to brew their coffee with, but I haven’t found this to make enough of a difference to justify the price, hassle and unecological choice. If you live on the west side of Tampere, you’re getting ground water from your tap anyway. I’m not, but the water is still ok.</p>

    <p>Still, you probably don’t want to reuse water that’s been sitting in the electric kettle for two days already. But you already knew that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>My own addition: Fresh Brew</strong></p>

    <p>Probably the biggest reason people seem to think that espresso-based drink are the “good” coffee, as opposed to filter coffee, is that in most cases filter coffee has been sitting on top of a hot plate for quite some time. Espresso drinks on the other hand are basically always made to order.</p>

    <p>Now, here’s the thing: coffee (the drink) does not stand heating. This includes everything from the hot plate of your coffeemaker to microwave oven to percolator. Quality coffee is good when hot, best when slightly less hot and still great when not that hot anymore. Actually it tastes quite awesome even when cold. </p>

    <p><strong>Lesson 4:</strong> <em>Don’t let your coffee stand in the coffee maker after it’s done.</em> If you need it to stay hot for longer, pour it into a vacuum bottle.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>With these lessons under our belt, here are a couple of practical tips for your coffee pleasure.</p>

<h2 id="quality-beans-in-tampere">Quality beans in Tampere</h2>

<p>Like you learned in lessons 1 and 2 above, you’re going to buy freshly roasted, whole beans. Finding them in Tampere is kind of tricky, but not impossible.</p>

<h3 id="by-mail">By mail</h3>

<p>Your best bet it pretty much always mail order. This is mostly because the best roasters only ship coffee right after roasting. This means that they settle down just the right amount during the days it takes for them to reach your mailbox and are thus ready to use.</p>

<p>My absolute favorite roaster is <a href="http://shop.squaremilecoffee.com/">Square Mile Coffee</a> in London. Pretty much all their coffee is direct trade. While the selection isn’t huge, you also cannot go wrong with any of their coffees. I recommend getting a <a href="http://shop.squaremilecoffee.com/collections/filter-subscriptions">subscription</a> from them, which means at the beginning of each month they will send you a bag of coffee fitting the season. If you’re not ready for a subscription, just order a bag or two. The shipping costs are pretty much the same as with any Finnish roaster. Note that they only roast twice a week, so your order might take a couple of days to ship.</p>

<p>Another great British roaster is <a href="http://www.hasbean.co.uk/">Has Bean Coffee</a>. Their selection is vast compared to Square Mile and includes lots of different types of coffees, including organic varieties. They also offer <a href="http://www.hasbean.co.uk/categories/Subscription-Coffee/">subscriptions</a> (both <a href="http://www.hasbean.co.uk/products/The-Twelve-Month-Coffee-Gift-%28roasted-Beans%29.html">monthly</a> and <a href="http://www.hasbean.co.uk/products/In-My-Mug-Subscription-Pack-%252d-12-Months-%2852-Weeks%29.html">weekly</a>) which are considerably cheaper than Square Mile’s. However, it’s worth noting that their bags (as most other roasters’) are 250 grams, as opposed to Square Mile’s 350 g.</p>

<h3 id="locally">Locally</h3>

<p>In my opinion, currently the best coffee roasted in Finland comes from <a href="http://www.turunkahvipaahtimo.fi/">Turun Kahvipaahtimo</a>. Unfortunately, they don’t have an online store, let alone subscriptions. Fortunately, <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=kahvila%20valo&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CDIQFjAA&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.kahvilavalo.fi%2F&amp;ei=Wg4UT7HoIuXk4QSVsIXVAw&amp;usg=AFQjCNFad635IFavO31Ic9-JwZehbymIaw&amp;sig2=ri5SfTtonRy_HCtSQsvy1g">Kahvila Valo</a> on <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;cid=0,0,2896588366309574865&amp;fb=1&amp;hq=kahvila+valo&amp;daddr=Puutarhakatu+11,+33210+Tampere,+Finland&amp;geocode=0,61.499224,23.758477">Puutarhakatu</a> sells their coffee. However, they seem to sell such limited amounts of it that it’s best to find out their shipping schedule to know when to go look for new beans.</p>

<p><a href="http://kaffaroastery.fi/">Kaffa</a> is a fairly new entrant in the Finnish coffee scene. Operating in Rööperi in the heart of Helsinki, Kaffa’s guys seem to put a fair amount of love and effort into their offerings. They have some interesting coffees such as the <a href="http://kaffaroastery.fi/products/india-monsoon-malabar">Indian Monsoon Malabar</a>, but on average they seem to me a bit more hit and miss than Turun Kahvipaahtimo. E.g. even though they say they only send freshly roasted coffee, I’ve often gotten weeks old coffee sent to me from their online store. However, Mama’s Corner sells their coffee in the market hall, and there you can be sure about the roasting date of the coffee. Unfortunately, the same disclaimer as with Valo and Turun Kahvipaahtimo applies: the coffee comes to the store every once in a while, so you can’t rely on it being totally fresh whenever you step into the shop.</p>

<p>The original local roastery in Tampere is called <a href="http://mokkamestarit.fi/">Mokkamestarit</a>. They roast a surprisingly varied selection of coffees, including fair trade, direct trade, organic and <a href="http://www.cupofexcellence.org/">Cup of Excellence</a> beans. Kahvila Valo sells a (very) limited selection of Mokkamestarit’s coffee. However, for the full selection you should probably visit their <a href="http://www.mokkamestarit.fi/index.php/menutehtaanmyymala">roastery shop</a> in <a href="http://maps.google.fi/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=fi&amp;geocode=&amp;q=kuukuja+8e&amp;aq=&amp;sll=62.593341,27.575684&amp;sspn=9.268238,28.256836&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Kuukuja+8,+33420+Tampere&amp;z=15">Vermo</a>. My issue with Mokkamestarit is that they don’t tell the exact roasting date at least with the coffees I’ve seen. Moreover, they set the expiry date to something ridiculously long like a year, so it might be difficult to make sure how fresh the coffee is. However, if you can make sure you get truly freshly roasted coffee from them, they are probably a fine option.</p>

<p>Just recently I learned about <a href="http://www.freshcoffee.fi/">Fresh Coffee Roastery</a>, which operates in Onkiniemi. Unfortunately, it seems that they neither have a shop at the roastery nor have a reseller in Tampere, so your only option is to rely on their web store. I have yet to taste their coffee, so I can’t really vouch for them.</p>

<h2 id="grinding-your-coffee">Grinding your coffee</h2>

<p>My advice is to start with a quality and grinder, not a cheap electric blade grinder. The important bit is to get a burr grinder, not a blade grinder. I use a Porlex hand grinder, which is stainless steel throughout, with ceramic burrs. Since the hopper is not plastic, it generates very little static so it’s very easy to get the grinds out of it. Another great thing about Porlex is that it fits perfectly inside an Aeropress, so they make a great travel kit together.</p>

<div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://skitch.com/jarkko/g3nqq/skitched-20120116-152547"><img src="https://img.skitch.com/20120116-pr39sg5137dtqc7kqdhh71ai2g.preview.jpg" alt="" /></a></div>

<p>Another hand grinder people seem to recommend is <a href="http://www.crema.fi/fi/products/hario/skerton.html?gclid=CJXBpODS1K0CFYMtmAodR195Fg">Hario Skerton</a>. I have not used it myself, but you shouldn’t go astray with either of them.</p>

<p>The downside of a hand grinder is that grinding coffee with one is fairly slow and their capacity is limited. Every time we have visitors for coffee (not really that often) I wish I had an electric grinder. Any other time, I don’t.</p>

<p>Another issue with hand grinders is that it is somewhat difficult to control the grind coarseness. It happens with a screw so it’s next to impossible to “store” different settings for different brewing techniques.</p>

<p>The upside of a hand grinder is that it doesn’t wake up the whole house, and grinding coffee with it is a nice morning ritual. If your arms are in bad shape, it probably counts as exercise as well.</p>

<p>I’ve decided not to get an electric grinder before I can justify getting a really good one. At the moment that would mean <a href="http://www.hasbean.co.uk/products/Mahlkonig-Vario-Coffee-Grinder.html">Mahlkönig Vario</a>.</p>

<h2 id="brewing-the-coffee">Brewing the coffee</h2>

<p>Everyone who gives a shit about coffee in Finland probably has a Moccamaster. The good news is that there’s no reason to get rid of it. However, (unless you have a model with a vacuum bottle) you should never let the brewed coffee stay on the hot plate after it’s ready. This means that if you want to serve hot coffee during a longer period, you need a good vacuum bottle.</p>

<p>That said, there’s something deeply gratifying in having more control over your brew. For that, there are several inexpensive options. These are what I use myself:</p>

<h3 id="chemex">Chemex</h3>

<div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://skitch.com/jarkko/g3nxr/img-0538"><img src="https://img.skitch.com/20120116-g39g3atd22bu78k1fdkg4megjp.preview.jpg" alt="IMG_0538" /></a></div>

<p>The legendary Chemex coffeemaker was invented in 1941 by Dr. Peter Schlumbohm. He’s famously quoted saying that “With this, even a moron can make good coffee.” To add to that, Chemex is on an ongoing <a href="http://www.moma.org/collection/object.php?object_id=1847">display in the Museum of Modern Art</a> in New York. We have an 8-cup version of the brewer and use it pretty much every morning.</p>

<h3 id="aeropress">Aeropress</h3>

<div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://skitch.com/jarkko/g3nxt/skitched-20120116-153016"><img src="https://img.skitch.com/20120116-nsdxwka3up78eqhtjjhguya3be.preview.jpg" alt="" /></a></div>

<p>While it lacks the elegant looks of a Chemex, <a href="http://aerobie.com/products/aeropress.htm">Aeropress</a> is a truly miraculous device. This inexpensive (and somewhat cheap-looking) device can extract some of the best brews from your beans and it does it in a time that really can’t be beaten. Like said above, an Aeropress makes a great travel kit with the Porlex grinder (and some quality beans) which means you can have great coffee wherever you go. Just add water.</p>

<p>Moreover, Aeropress is very easy to clean up. After the brew, you just pluck the filter and grinds into a biodegradable waste container and rinse the device with hot water. This makes Aeropress also a great office coffeemaker. Using it will first get you some amused glances, and then some ridicule. And then, until you realized what happened, everyone will be using you ‘press. At least that’s what I imagine would happen. I don’t really have any officemates so I extrapolated from my wife.</p>

<h2 id="i-dont-have-time-for-this-just-tell-me-where-to-get-great-coffee-in-tampere">I don’t have time for this, just tell me where to get great coffee in Tampere.</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.kahvilavalo.fi/">Kahvila Valo</a>. They have a horrible website but are indeed a great, somewhat rustic café. Like said, they sell a decent selection of freshly roasted beans from different roasters. Most importantly, they have recently added several new brewing methods into their arsenal: Aeropress, Chemex and <a href="http://theotherblackstuff.ie/machines/abid-clever-coffee-dripper/">Abid Clever dripper</a>. My favorite cup of coffee there is a strong smooth Kenyan made with Abid.</p>

<p>Unfortunately Valo only opens at 11AM, so it’s not suitable for morning coffee. On the flipside, it is more or less empty until late afternoon, so it’s a great place to hack in if you’re looking for a quiet office outside the office. They also serve light food such as lunch salads, sandwiches and soups.</p>

<p>Jaakko Halmetoja says nice words about <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Taikapapu">Kahvila Taikapapu</a>. I haven’t checked them out myself yet. </p>

<h2 id="where-to-go-next">Where to go next?</h2>

<p>Filter coffee is an affair that is easy to get into, but that has a pretty much limitless depth. On theoretical level, I’d recommend reading Has Bean’s <a href="http://coffee101.co.uk/">Coffee 101</a> and Mathias Meyer’s <a href="http://holgarific.net/?p=707">Beginner’s Shopping Guide to Filter Coffee Gear</a>. But most importantly, just get the bare minimum of needed equipment – e.g. an Aeropress with a Porlex grinder –, some quality beans and start experimenting.</p>

<p>And enjoy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby, meet QuickRoute]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2012/01/02/ruby-meet-quickroute/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2012/01/02/ruby-meet-quickroute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While I missed the tradition of releasing Ruby gems on the Christmas day, I did meet my own tradition of not doing anything with the computer that day. That said, I had something interesting in the works that just needed to be wrapped up as a Ruby gem—namely, a library for parsing the GPS data out of JPEG files produced by <a href="http://www.matstroeng.se/quickroute/en/">QuickRoute</a>. Without further ado, may I present <a href="https://github.com/jarkko/quickroute-ruby">quickroute-ruby</a>.</p>

<p>The task wasn’t exactly trivial, as the data is embedded in binary format in an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPEG_File_Interchange_Format#JFIF_segment_format">APP0 segment</a> inside the image. Moreover, the data format was basically undocumented. However, with the help of <a href="http://www.matstroeng.se/">Mats</a> I managed to reverse-engineer the original C# and PHP libraries to an extent that I seemed to get correct output out of the file.</p>

<p>The library is still very young, and while it seems to work correctly with my test images, I have no doubt there are a bunch of bugs hidden. If you seem to run into one, please file an <a href="https://github.com/jarkko/quickroute-ruby/issues">issue in the tracker</a>, or better yet, send me a <a href="https://github.com/jarkko/quickroute-ruby/pulls">pull request</a> with a test-driven fix.</p>

<p>For usage, check out the GitHub page. I’ll work on cleaning up the code and writing some more documentation in the coming days, but the code itself should be fairly self-explanatory.</p>

<p>Happy New Year!</p>

<p><strong>P.S</strong> <a href="https://github.com/jarkko/quickroute-gps">I’m also mirroring</a> the complete (GPL licensed) <a href="http://code.google.com/p/quickroute-gps/">QuickRoute C# code repository</a> on GitHub. So if you prefer working with Git instead of Subversion + Google Code, you might want to start off there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blade Runner]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2011/09/30/blade-runner/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2011/09/30/blade-runner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The launch of Amazon’s new Kindles has already been analyzed to near death, so I’m not going to dive too deep in that general discussion. What struck me as interesting, though, was <a href="http://daringfireball.net/">John Gruber’s analysis</a> of the new models being US-only:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Production must be tight on the Fire and Touch models, as well, because they’re only being offered in the U.S. for now. The only new Kindle for sale outside the U.S. is the $79 non-touch model.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now here’s the thing: it’s clear that Amazon is in the razor blade business. At $199, Kindle Fire either has a razor-thin margin or is sold at a loss. <a href="http://www.appleinsider.com/articles/11/09/28/piper_jaffray_estimates_amazon_will_lose_50_per_kindle_fire.html">According to Piper Jaffray’s Gene Munster</a> Amazon is taking a hit of $50 for every device it sells. If that’s the case, it must make up for that selling content, which is its bread-and-butter business.</p>

<p>However, selling content such as books, music and movies is also a low-margin business. That means Amazon has to sell a shitload of content to make up for the potential losses it makes with the Fire. Fortunately for Amazon, its customers are people who <em>do</em> spend a lot of money online – maybe second only to Apple. That’s probably the case only in US, though. International clients are likely to spend far less money on Amazon, because of narrower selection of books in their language, and because of movies and TV shows not being available, at all. As <a href="http://www.asymco.com/2011/09/30/the-case-against-the-kindle-as-a-low-end-tablet-disruption/">Horace Dediu points out</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The problem is that services don’t scale as well as products. Consider that none of the content streams that Amazon will depend on are available outside the US. The Kindle has not been a strong seller internationally. This is because book rights are limited to national boundaries as are movie rights and song rights. Apple has only this week finally completed the rollout of iTunes music to all of Europe! A process that took almost a decade.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So what if the production capacity isn’t the only reason for the new Kindle models being US-only? What if – given Amazon’s current production costs and international licensing deals – they just can’t see themselves selling enough razor blades to make up for the cost of the razor?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iTunes doesn't recognize your iPhone or iPad anymore? Here's the fix.]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2011/08/18/itunes-doesn-t-recognize-your-iphone-or-ipad-anymore-here-s-the-fix/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2011/08/18/itunes-doesn-t-recognize-your-iphone-or-ipad-anymore-here-s-the-fix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Somewhere between updating OS X to Lion and iTunes to version 10.4 iTunes stopped recognizing both my iPhone and my iPad. What’s weirder, even though System information saw both devices, my iPad also showed the disappointing “Not Charging” message in its status bar. The iPhone, which doesn’t demand as high a voltage from the port, did charge, though.</p>

<p>The web is full of different instructions on how to fix this kind of a situation. The gist of them all is basically to restart the device, restart the computer and if these won’t help, reinstall iTunes. There is even a <a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/ht1747">knowledge base article</a> on the Apple support pages with these instructions.</p>

<p>The problem is, Lion doesn’t let you move iTunes to the Trash because it is “needed by the operating system”<sup id="fnl_201108180101"><a href="#fn_201108180101">1</a></sup>, contrary to what the aforementioned article says<sup id="fnl_201108180102"><a href="#fn_201108180102">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Fortunately, OS X is built on the shoulders of Unix giants, so here’s how I managed to fix the problem.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Open up Terminal.app, e.g. using Spotlight.
<img src="https://img.skitch.com/20110818-826b9ngu72e4cauhp1m61ape24.jpg" alt="Find Terminal using Spotlight search" /></li>
  <li>
    <p>Move the iTunes.app directory to a temporary place. Note that you need sudo to be able to actually move the folder.</p>

    <pre><code> $ mkdir -p ~/temp; cd /Applications; sudo mv iTunes.app ~/temp
</code></pre>
  </li>
  <li>Download the <a href="http://www.apple.com/itunes/download/">latest iTunes version</a> from Apple’s website and run through the installation process.</li>
  <li>There is no step four. iTunes should now recognize your devices again.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Warning</strong>. This procedure fixed the issue for me. It should not affect your iTunes library (which is normally located in <code>~/Music/iTunes</code>) or preferences (which reside in <code>~/Library/iTunes</code>). However, there is no guarantee that it will work for you. Don’t hold me accountable if you mess up your iTunes library. What’s more important, <em>make sure you have backups of everything before you start</em>.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn_201108180101">
<p>After reinstalling iTunes this error mysteriously disappeared, i.e. I am now able to drag the iTunes.app folder to the trash just fine.&nbsp;<a href="#fnl_201108180101">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn_201108180102">
<p>To be fair, the article is dated back to last December and has not been updated to the Lion era. Which begs the question, why not?&nbsp;<a href="#fnl_201108180102">&#8617;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Compensation. Supercompensation.]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2010/11/09/compensation-supercompensation/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2010/11/09/compensation-supercompensation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This the second part of The Road to <a href="http://www.rubyconf5k.com">RubyConf XK</a>, a series of articles about running training. Don’t miss the <a href="http://jlaine.net/2010/11/1/the-road-to-rubyconf-xk-why-run">first part</a>.</em></p>

<p>For many, it is enough to know that running keeps you fit. But if you’re training with a goal in mind (be it a specific time on marathon or just to get into better shape), it is useful to know a bit about the physiology of physical training.</p>

<p>I’ll start by letting you into a secret. From the outset, you might think that exercise makes you fitter. Actually, exactly the opposite is true. Exercise makes you less fit.</p>

<p>But hey, I hear you say. Why do we then train at all? Let me explain.</p>

<p>In sports science, the training effect can be described with a simple graph:</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20101109-eq9g1xfn319ecwitqmr18kbgnx.png" alt="Supercompensation effect" /></p>

<p><em>Figure 1. Supercompensation effect.</em></p>

<p>In the graph, the red parts are training sessions, during which the fitness level of our persevering hero goes down<a href="#fn201011020101"><sup id="ln201011020101">1</sup></a>. Then, during the <em>rest</em> phase (marked green) the level goes back up to where it was. However—and this is the interesting part—it doesn’t stop there. Because of evolution, intelligent design or a turn of the wrist of the flying spaghetti monster, the human body is an adaptive organism. It basically thinks, “Gee, I was hit really hard during that last workout, so I’ll be clever and hoard some extra jelly in order to be prepared for the next one”. And thus it steps beyond its initial level of fitness to the land of the unknown. This effect is known as <em>supercompensation</em>.</p>

<p>Supercompensation is a funny thing. It happens in many different training effects, be it strength, aerobic performance, or maximum running speed. As we’ll see later, the effect is also used on many timescales in training programs, from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_training">intervals</a> within a single workout to training sessions to days to weeks or even longer training periods.</p>

<p>From the supercompensation graph above we can draw three corollaries:</p>

<ul>
  <li>You should train at the optimal point of the rest phase.</li>
  <li>You should make the recovery curve as steep as possible.</li>
  <li>You should find an optimal rhythm to your training.</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, let’s look at each of these in more detail.</p>

<h3 id="goal-1-train-at-the-optimal-moment">Goal 1: train at the optimal moment</h3>

<p>In a perfect world, training would always happen at the very top of the supercompensation curve. In reality, that is of course not possible. First of all, the whole graph is a vast oversimplification. There is no single thing called fitness. Rather, there are several aspects to it such as muscle condition, energy level and general fatigue.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it is important to understand the timing of hard trainings. If you always train too soon after the previous tiring exercise, the curve will never reach the supercompensation state but rather top off before the previous high level. Continuing this for too long can cause what is called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overtraining">overtraining</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20101109-jar82y59yh421m59a353j6iwui.png" alt="Overtraining" /></p>

<p><em>Figure 2. Overtraining. Leaving too little time between hard workouts leads to decrease of the fitness level.</em></p>

<p>Overtraining is a condition with symptoms like general feeling of tiredness, sleep problems, high rest and <a href="http://www.wholefitness.com/overtraintest.html">orthostatic</a> heart rate. Recovering from severe overtraining can easily take months. Many top athletes who have trained themselves too far have never recovered. It is thus important to train on a level that is suitable for your current fitness. You can’t start an olympic-level training program if you have not run a mile in last five years.</p>

<p>On the other hand, if you leave too much time between the workouts (which is frankly far more common among us), the supercompensation effect will fade out and your body will return back to the previous level or even lower.</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20101109-xs5gwjg4r6uqk2ydatx9ejquw.png" alt="Training too seldom" /></p>

<p><em>Figure 3. Workouts too far apart. The training effect fades away between them.</em></p>

<h3 id="goal-2-recuperate-as-fast-as-possible">Goal 2: Recuperate as fast as possible</h3>

<p>Like said in the beginning, your fitness doesn’t improve while training, it improves while resting. Assuming that you always exercise at the optimal moment, the next thing you can do to optimize the training effect is to make the recovery period as quick as possible. This will allow you do more training-recovery loops within the same amount of time.</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20101109-dt65txytptx77kerydywn4sd7g.png" alt="Faster recovery allows for more workouts in the same amount of time" /></p>

<p><em>Figure 4. Faster recovery allows for more workouts in the same amount of time, thus resulting in faster increase of fitness.</em></p>

<p>There are a vast amount of ways to shorten your recovery time. The effectiveness of many of them depends on the individual. However, many if not most of them have been scientifically proven to accelerate the process of recuperation. Just remember that doing nothing at all rarely is the fastest way to recover.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Energy</strong>: Try to get energy as fast as possible after the training. A rule of thumb is something quick (such as a recovery drink or bar) within 30 minutes and a warm meal within 2 hours. This helps to start the refill process of glycogen<a href="#fn201011020102"><sup id="ln201011020102">2</sup></a> stores in the muscles and to get them out of a catabolic state. The most important constituent in the recovery process are carbohydrates (the recommended amount for quick recovery is 10g for each 10kg in your body weight), so forget low-carb diets if you plan to go by a real training program<a href="#fn201011020103"><sup id="ln201011020103">3</sup></a>. Proteins are not nearly as important in endurance sports as carbs, but they have been proven to improve the carbohydrate intake and glycogen restoration. The recommended amount of proteins right after a workout is about 3g for each 10kg of your body mass.</li>
  <li><strong>Sleep</strong>: Not only do you rest best while asleep, your body also produces more human growth hormone when asleep<a href="#fn201011020104"><sup id="ln201011020104">4</sup></a>, which quickens the recovery process in muscles. It is important to note that the physical restitution happens mostly in the deep non-REM sleep<a href="#fn201011020105"><sup id="ln201011020105">5</sup></a>, so forget polyphasic sleep and other gimmicks. 9 hours each night and a one-hour nap during the afternoon downswing is <em>not</em> over the top.</li>
  <li><strong>Stretching</strong>: Stretching keeps your muscles more elastic by lengthening the individual muscle fibers and helps to get the waste products flowing away from the muscles by increasing blood circulation. On top of that, too tight muscles and tendons often cause injuries in the long run, and make your stride shorter and running posture unnatural.</li>
  <li><strong>Massage</strong>: The same as with stretching. Note that you don’t have to get an appointment from a masseuse (although it doesn’t hurt, except sometimes, literally), you can help the recovery process of your muscles by rubbing them yourself.</li>
  <li><strong>Hot</strong>: Especially in cold weather, something like sauna helps your muscles to relax. However, make sure you regain the liquids and electrolytes lost when sweating (applies to warm bath as well).</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/morgaine/3093958622/in/photostream/"><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3146/3093958622_ca5b487d27_m.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Cold</strong>: A paradox, huh? Not at all. While warmth helps your muscles to relax, cold on one hand mitigates swelling and micro-trauma, and on the other, stimulates muscles which helps them recover faster. Works especially well when alternated with hot.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/maaniemi/405930999/in/photostream/"><img src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/171/405930999_e380565bf8_m.jpg" alt="Ice swimming" /></a></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/people/maaniemi/">Tero Maaniemi</a>.</em></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>More training</strong>: More things that sound like a paradox. After tough workouts, very easy training is often way better for recovery than just pure rest, which often causes muscle stiffness and thus makes the next hard exercise less effective. Even within interval workouts it’s proven to be better to slowly run between the heats than to just stand still.</li>
  <li><strong>Electrical muscle stimulation</strong>: Ok, this is a gimmick but if you’re serious about exercise and don’t mind shelling out a few hundred bucks, an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electrical_muscle_stimulation">electrical muscle stimulation</a> machine can be quite a versatile help in both helping the muscles to recuperate and to treat injuries.</li>
</ul>

<p>On the other side of the equation, there are a few things that will slow down the recovery process and that you should  avoid if possible.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Being sick</strong>: If you’re sick your energy goes into fighting the disease instead of recuperating from the training. Unlike you might think, there <em>are</em> things you can do to avoid many common illnesses such as flu.</li>
  <li><strong>Lack of sleep</strong>: See <em>sleep</em> above.</li>
  <li><strong>Jet lag</strong>: Pretty much the same reasons as with lack of sleep.</li>
  <li><strong>Stress</strong>: Stress and overtraining form a vicious cycle and are (quite literally) a killer combo.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="goal-3-perfect-rhythm">Goal 3: Perfect rhythm</h3>

<p>Like said above, the supercompensation effect happens on many levels. Within single workouts such as interval trainings, between workout sessions and days, and even between weeks. Therefore, unlike we indicated in goal #1, there might not be a single optimal moment for a training on all those timescales. Sometimes it makes sense to train even while tired, especially on training camps. On the other hand, after harder periods of training you might need to take it easier for a whole week before doing another hard workout.</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20101109-xmng24ict3ac3w652fi5ingsnr.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><em>Figure 5. Supercompensation on both workout and weekly level.</em></p>

<p>It is thus important to find a good rhythm for your training program. This should happen on one hand both on short (day/workout) long (between weeks) timeframe; on the other hand on both workout intensity, length and type level. Some examples:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A typical week rhythm for training might be easy, moderate, moderate-hard, hard, weekly hours being something like 6, 10, 14 and 18 hours.</li>
  <li>One rule of thumb rhythm (for an orienteer) for individual days or workouts during the base training season is long, strength, hard, easy, long, strength, easy. This has seven points so it’s either a weekly (if you train once a day) or half-weekly (if you train twice a day) program. The point of this rhythm is that typically fast workouts are not that effective after a long training. On the other hand, the strength-fast pair is typically pretty effective in putting the strength picked up from the gym into practice.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>If you read the training schedules of some famous athletes, you can see that there are no two similar programs. While sport science has evolved massively in the last 60 years, there is still no one right way to exercise that would work for everyone or even for the same person in different situations. You thus need to find what works best for you, which is no small feat.</p>

<p>However, understanding the scientific basics of training a human body will help you assess the training programs you find and to choose the program that works best for you. You are thus in way better position than for example <a href="http://runningtimes.com/Article.aspx?ArticleID=5518">Emil Zatopek</a>, who spent years and years shuffling different training programs, from insane mileages to interval training in snow (which both worked well for him) to maximum strength training (which didn’t). So since we’re allowed to, let’s not be shy about running on the shoulders of giants.</p>

<h3 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h3>

<p><sup id="fn201011020101">1</sup> The reason for this is that training is a <a href="http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iupac/bioinorg/CD.html#8">catabolic</a> process, where large molecules are broken into smaller ones, at the same time releasing energy. <a href="#ln201011020101">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011020102">2</sup> Glycogen is the stored carbohydrate in muscles that human body <a href="http://www.unm.edu/~lkravitz/Article%20folder/glycogen.html">preferably uses as energy in sustained physical exercise</a>.<a href="#fn201011020106"><sup id="ln201011020106">6</sup></a> <a href="#ln201011020106">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011020103">3</sup> Williams, Raven, Fogt and Ivy: <a href="http://www.hawaii.edu/hivandaids/Effects%20of%20Recovery%20Beverages%20on%20Glycogen%20Restoration%20and%20Endurance%20Exercise%20Performance.pdf">Effects of Recovery Beverages on Glycogen Restoration and Endurance Exercise Performance</a>. <a href="#ln201011020103">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011020104">4</sup> Van Cauter et al: <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6WG5-4CBD3JV-6&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=06%2F30%2F2004&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=da02c5f5801677a388afadb7639467c8&amp;searchtype=a">Reciprocal interactions between the GH axis and sleep</a>. <a href="#ln201011020104">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011020105">5</sup> Weissblut: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0449004023/?tag=jlainenet-20">Healthy Sleep Habits, Happy Child</a>. <a href="#ln201011020105">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011020106">6</sup> Gotta love research made by Lenny Kravitz. <a href="#ln201011020106">?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Road to RubyConf Xk: Why run?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2010/11/01/the-road-to-rubyconf-xk-why-run/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2010/11/01/the-road-to-rubyconf-xk-why-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="about-the-road-to-rubyconfxk">About The Road to RubyConfXk</h3>

<p><em>This is a series of articles that I’m writing paving the road to <a href="http://rubyconf5k.com/">RubyConf Xk</a>, the second installment of the running event at the yearly <a href="http://rubyconf.org/">RubyConf</a>. This is the pilot episode of the series. Next parts will explore several diverse topics loosely related to running.</em></p>

<p>I’ll have to start with a confession. If you’re looking for experiences from someone who knows a lot about how to start to run, I’m not the right person. While I technically did start to run, that happened when I was only a few years old. I don’t remember much from those days. Unlike many others, I never stopped running after that. So maybe the right thing to say is I don’t know much about <em>re</em>starting to run.</p>

<p>Also, I’m not a <em>real</em> runner at all. I’m first and foremost an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orienteering">orienteer</a> and like many other sports as well. Likewise, while I mostly talk about running in this series, many if not most of the lessons can be directly applied to other endurance sports as well.</p>

<p>However.</p>

<p>Running is a natural way to move, and to me, the purest form of all sports. For millions of years, it was the fastest way to move on land known to mankind. It is the way children naturally move when they play, often hours every day<a href="#fn201011010101"><sup id="ln201011010101">1</sup></a>. At some point, we slip away from this much exercise (often all the way down to nothing).</p>

<p>Why is this bad? That’s what the rest of this article tries to uncover.</p>

<h3 id="health">Health</h3>

<p>This is kind of stating the obvious (and—I hope—preaching to the choir), so I’m going to keep this short. Exercise makes you healthier, it makes you live longer and it makes you feel better here and now. There, I’ve said it. Now for something you might <em>not</em> have considered.</p>

<h3 id="quiet-time">Quiet time</h3>

<p>In a recent <a href="http://wiki.twit.tv/wiki/MacBreak_Weekly_214">MacBreak Weekly episode</a>, Andy Ihnatko mentioned Nicholas Carr’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0393072223/?tag=jlainenet-20">The Shallows: What the Internet Is Doing to Our Brains</a>. In the book, Carr explores what the constant stream of bit-size information and interruptions coming from the internet is doing to our brains. Whether or not you agree with his conclusions<a href="#fn201011010102"><sup id="ln201011010102">2</sup></a>, it’s clear that in this age of uninterrupted interruptions, our brain needs some quiet time. Now that <a href="http://daringfireball.net/2009/12/the_tablet">we can surf on the ‘net while sitting in the bathroom</a>, there are fewer and fewer places where we can really sit back (either figuratively or literally) and reflect on things.</p>

<p>For me, going for a run (or a bike ride) is often the asylum where I’m really able to gather my thoughts and let ideas fly free. Even if I decide to listen to a podcast or an audiobook while running, I often drift off into deep thoughts on how to apply the ideas presented through the phones to my own current context.</p>

<p>But having quiet time is not the only reason why many prominent figures tell they get most of their ideas while running, walking and biking.</p>

<h3 id="exercise-boosts-brain-power">“Exercise boosts brain power”</h3>

<p>In his seminal book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0979777704/?tag=jlainenet-20">Brain Rules</a>, molecular biologist John Medina explains in readable and fascinating way how the most important organ of every knowledge worker—our brain—works<a href="#fn201011010103"><sup id="ln201011010103">3</sup></a>. The title of this section is a direct copy of the name of his first <em>rule</em>. As it turns out, the increased oxygen supply to the brain caused by exercise has been shown to not only cause long-term improvement in cognition, but also immediate results. We are even smarter than normally <em>during</em> the exercise. This caused Medina to go so far as to suggest deploying treadmills in classrooms and cubicles. While that’s an interesting idea (that quite a few people have actually made <a href="http://www.treadmilldeskinc.com/treadmill_desk_exec.html">reality</a>), the most important thing is that you exercise.<a href="#fn201011010104"><sup id="ln201011010104">4</sup></a></p>

<h3 id="personal-addendum-experiences">Personal addendum: experiences</h3>

<p>For many runners, every vacation is equal to a training camp. While some might say this is bringing work to holiday, it has some hidden benefits as well.</p>

<p>To me, holidays are all about experiences. I’m really not interested in lying on the beach or by the pool for very long. And this is where combining running with sightseeing comes in.</p>

<p>You could certainly gain many of the same experiences by driving a car to the spot (when it’s possible). However, I have a theory (based on highly anecdotal evidence) that running accentuates that experience. And it seems there is some research that (loosely) supports my theory.</p>

<p>I got one of the ideas from Dan Ariely’s book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0061995037/?tag=jlainenet-20">The Upside of Irrationality</a><a href="#fn201011010105"><sup id="ln201011010105">5</sup></a>. In it he explains the so-called Ikea effect, which effectively means we’re most attached to things we made ourselves, or had to go through effort to attain. This might explain why the views from a mountaintop feel so much more magnificent if you ran or climbed up rather than took a gondola.</p>

<p>Another possible explanation to the phenomenon is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endorphin#Runner.27s_high">runner’s high</a>, which would (whether the cause of the high is endorphin, anandamide or whatnot) quite naturally affect the strength of the perceived experience.</p>

<p>A case study of this is our 6-week workcation in New Zealand, which turned into more of a normal vacation when my laptop died while driving down the South Island.</p>

<p>During the trip, we</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Ran to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Te_Whanganui-A-Hei_(Cathedral_Cove\)">Cathedral Cove</a>;</p>

    <p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/3272915811/in/set-72157613678662906/"><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3331/3272915811_2e49b2a200.jpg" alt="Cathedral Cove" /></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ran hill intervals on <a href="http://www.qctrack.co.nz/">Queen Charlotte Track</a>;</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ran up and down the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepler_Track">Kepler Track</a><a href="#fn201011010106"><sup id="ln201011010106">6</sup></a>;</p>

    <p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/5137657238/"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1406/5137657238_789c8e234c.jpg" alt="Running down the Kepler Track" /></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ran back and forth the riverfront in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur%27s_Pass_(mountain_pass\)">Arthur’s Pass</a> since the weather forecast was so bad we didn’t dare to go up the mountain;</p>

    <p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/5137528302/in/set-72157613678662906/"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1080/5137528302_b42a260b18.jpg" alt="Arthur's Pass" /></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Kayaked up the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abel_Tasman_National_Park">Abel Tasman National Park</a> and ran back on the hiking trails;</p>

    <p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/5137053155/"><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4069/5137053155_7fc3b0aa65.jpg" alt="Abel Tasman" /></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ran back and forth the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tongariro_Northern_Circuit">Tongariro Northern Circuit</a>.</p>

    <p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/5137529374/in/set-72157613678662906/"><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4151/5137529374_01a735acc1.jpg" alt="Tongariro Northern Circuit" /></a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>These are some of the fondest memories of my whole life. I wouldn’t want to have experienced them any other way.</p>

<h4 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h4>

<p><sup id="fn201011010101">1</sup> Well, they should. The recommended amount of daily exercise for a child is around 2 hours. <a href="#ln201011010101">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011010102">2</sup> Carr is a known internet critic and sceptic so he might have an axe to grind even in its effects on us. <a href="#ln201011010102">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011010103">3</sup> Don’t miss the interviews (<a href="http://podcast.rubyonrails.org/programs/1/episodes/john-medina">1</a>, <a href="http://podcast.rubyonrails.org/programs/1/episodes/john-medina-on-brain-rules-for-baby-part-i">2</a>, <a href="http://podcast.rubyonrails.org/programs/1/episodes/john-medina-on-brain-rules-for-baby-part-ii">3</a>) Geoffrey Grosenbach has made with Medina in the Ruby on Rails podcast. <a href="#ln201011010103">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011010104">4</sup> If you’re interested in the effects exercise causes to your brain, you might want to take a look at (besides Medina’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/John-Medina/e/B002BLNBUW/ref=ntt_athr_dp_pel_1&amp;tag=jlainenet-20">books</a>) John J. Ratey’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0316113506/?tag=jlainenet-20">Spark: The Revolutionary New Science of Exercise and the Brain</a> <a href="#ln201011010104">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011010105">5</sup> The Upside of Irrationality is the successor of Ariely’s highly successful book on behavioral economics, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0061353248/?tag=jlainenet-20">Predictably Irrational</a> <a href="#ln201011010105">?</a></p>

<p><sup id="fn201011010106">6</sup> We did not, however, go as far as our friends who ran around the whole 60 km track (with 1200m height difference between the highest and lowest point) in a day. <a href="#ln201011010106">?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to quickly fix Safari 5 Reader typography]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2010/06/09/how-to-quickly-fix-safari-5-reader-typography/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2010/06/09/how-to-quickly-fix-safari-5-reader-typography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really like the clutter-free reading experience the new <a href="http://www.apple.com/safari/whats-new.html#reader">Reader</a> feature in <a href="http://www.apple.com/safari/">Safari 5</a> brings. However, what I don&#8217;t like too much is the standard html rendering it uses for typography. The full fix for this would be to write a Safari extension to run the whole text through <a href="http://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a> or the very least through the <a href="http://www.bramstein.com/projects/typeset/">Knuth &amp; Plass</a> algorithm.</p>
<p>However, a quick fix for the horrible justified text is this:</p>
<p>Open the contents of Applications/Safari.app:</p>
<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20100609-8tynrxcjdgwt16bcr69fq1rsge.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>Then open Resources/Reader.html in a text editor.</p>
<p>Around line 82 there is a <span class="caps">CSS</span> rule for <code>.page</code>. Update it to left-align the paragraphs:</p>
<p><code class="css">&lt;pre&gt;
.page {
    font: 20px Palatino, Georgia, Times, "Times New Roman", serif;
    line-height: 160%;
    text-align: left !important;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
</code></p>
<p>Use <code>!important</code> as well, just to make sure. Save the file (you might need to type in your password here), and you&#8217;re done!</p>
<p>If you dislike Palatino, you can of course edit the <span class="caps">CSS</span> to your heart&#8217;s content. For me, the biggest beef were the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_(typography)">rivers</a> flowing through the text when using the default justified alignment.</p>
<p><a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/3101464/safari-reader.png"><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/3101464/safari-reader-small.png" alt="" /></a></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at Frozen Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2010/03/23/speaking-at-frozen-rails/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2010/03/23/speaking-at-frozen-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20100323-qaibjnb3ahyjk79i89kc8rsg8u.png" alt="" /></p>
<p>The first-ever Ruby/Rails conference in Finland, <a href="http://frozenrails.eu">Frozen Rails</a>, is going to take place May 7th in Helsinki. The speaker lineup is top notch, including three <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/core">Rails core team</a> members and the inimitable <a href="http://defunkt.github.com/">Chris Wanstrath</a>. For an unknown reason, in the midst of these high profile guys, a random guy from Tampere has ended up in the speaker list. Yours truly has the honorable (and somewhat frightening) job to wrap up the conference with an ending talk.</p>
<p>My talk is tentatively titled &#8220;Of Perfection, Perfectionism and Perfect Web Apps&#8221;. It will be less of a technical talk and more a critical, personal, humorous and hopefully entertaining performance about the previous decade spent writing various kinds of web sites and apps.</p>
<p>If you still haven&#8217;t secured your ticket, hurry up! The 99€ <a href="http://frozenrails.eu/information#pricing">early bird price</a> goes out tonight.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 guaranteed ways to make me block you on Twitter]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2010/03/06/6-bulletproof-ways-to-make-me-block-you-on-twitter/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2010/03/06/6-bulletproof-ways-to-make-me-block-you-on-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For me Twitter serves two purposes:</p>

<ol>
  <li>It helps me stay in contact with people I know but am unable to see often because they live on another side of the world or just because I’m a hermit working from home and never get out.</li>
  <li>It is a moderated feed of interesting content on the web.</li>
</ol>

<p>These purposes shall thus form the frame of reference for the rest of this article.</p>

<hr />

<p>One cool thing about Twitter is that it can be pretty much spam-free as far as it affects an individual user. Sure, there are lots of spammers around but they don’t really bother you much since the only exposure to them you’ll ever get is the single email you receive when someone follows you. You can turn off that notification.</p>

<p>In one end of the spectrum in how you handle followers on Twitter is to act like <a href="http://twitter.com/nzkoz/">Koz</a>: you let everyone follow you, even spammers. That can lead to a healthy number of followers, and the count will probably increase exponentially. The downside is that most of the followers will meet at least some criteria of the word “spammer”. This ratio will also probably get worse over time because the more followers you have the easier spammers will find you. But hey, at least you can brag about the hundreds of thousands of followers you have.</p>

<p>The polar opposite approach is to only allow your friends to follow you. This will basically make Twitter what Facebook used to be before it gave in to the dark side. Locking up your updates means that Twitter is a radically different tool for you, because you can’t use it to broadcast anything to the public. That’s fine for some people. However, it would totally defeat the second purpose I have for Twitter so it’s not an option for me.</p>

<p>My policy is somewhere between the two ends. Generally, I let everyone follow me. Just don’t expect me to follow you back. I want to keep my twitter feed palatable, so I only follow people based on the interestingness of their tweets. There are, however, a couple of jackass rules that do make me block you from my followers list.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Let’s get the obvious case done with first: <strong>your posts look anything like this</strong>:</li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>“how to get 16000+ followers in 90 days, fully automated”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>or</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“RECEIVE GUARANTEED $125 Commission When You Sign Up For FREE Advertisement!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have a word for that: spam. And not only will I block you, I <em>will</em> hit the “Report spam” button. I don’t care if you are the leading Twitter follower expert in the world. I just don’t care.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>You clearly auto-followed me based on something I tweeted.</strong> A year or so ago I tweeted about having watched the film “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000I5Y8FU?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=jlainenet-20&amp;linkCode=xm2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creativeASIN=B000I5Y8FU">Who killed the electric car?</a>”. I was immediately followed by @evcast, a podcast about electric cars. It was obvious that my tweet had sparked the action, since I had never heard of EVCast and I’m 100% sure they didn’t know about me either.</li>
</ol>

<p>A curious anecdote about this is that while automatically following me annoyed the hell out of me and I did block the Twitter account, I still ended up subscribing to the podcast, which is actually quite good and interesting. I wouldn’t recommend copying the habit, though. When the guy behind EVCast, Bo Bennett, later auto-followed me with another Twitter account (one for his own content management system product) after I mentioned the acronym “CMS” in a tweet, I had no qualms about blocking him.</p>

<p>Auto-following is a really pathetic form of <a href="http://twitter-fail.com/tag/follower-whoring/">follower-whoring</a>, based on the assumption that people are flattered by you following them and follow you back as a favor. Just don’t do it no matter what self-acclaimed Twitter gurus (you know, the ones tweeting like in point #1) tell you. Just don’t.</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20100306-cybx79jm7ejgy5ede3k2stx3mi.png" alt="Bo Bennett is following you" /></p>

<pre><code>---
</code></pre>

<p>The two first points in this list were pretty much black and white rules: break them and you’re out. The rest of the list consists of heuristics. Breaking one of them doesn’t necessarily put you onto the black list, but it does raise a flag. Combined, getting two or more hits is very likely to rule you out.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Make each entry start with the words “New blog post”</strong>.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20100306-ket53taiq86ni3fwjsf9c9tpc8.png" alt="New blog post" /></p>

<p>That looks like it’s an automated tweet from your blog software (which it probably is). For me, Twitter is all about authenticity and intimacy.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Make each entry end with a link to your blog post.</strong> Scratch that, make each entry end with a link, period. The link will most likely be a shortened url anyway, so I have no way of knowing where it points to. I’ll thus assume the worst: <em>your own blog post</em>.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is a more subtle variation of rule #3 and the same comments apply. Let me elaborate a bit more about that, though.</p>

<p>This rule is irrelevant if you are an actual friend and thus meet the #1 criteria in my Twitter usage pattern. For the second point, remember the word <em>moderated</em>. I have reduced my consumption of RSS feeds recently in favor of getting my daily fix of interesting content from my Twitter feed. If all you do is link to your own posts, you’re not contributing to the ecosystem and thus I have no business with you.</p>

<p>This is not to say you couldn’t have an automated Twitter feed for your blog. Just don’t make it your personal Twitter account. A good example is John Gruber, who has both a personal account and another one for Daring Fireball. Of course, the whole DF feed is already so well moderated that I’m following it as well as Gruber’s own account.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Follow more than 10 times as many people as who follow you.</strong> Like said, this is not an absolute measure but a heuristic that tells your Twitter usage pattern doesn’t really fit mine. What it basically tells me is that you’re following people very aggressively and/or you’re not very interesting because people are not following you in return. Either way it reeks of follower-whoring. This can be forgiven if you’re new to Twitter and have only a few followers.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20100306-f4paamgierb752a64ipr97m8hj.png" alt="" /></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Follow more than 1000 people.</strong> Same as above. If you follow a ridiculous amount of people it’s pretty clear that you cannot <em>really</em> follow them all.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>Generally, why do people break these rules? To get more followers. It’s the classic get rich quick scheme. The social media consultants are today’s version of charlatans who sell dreams of risk-free, high-interest investments and shortcuts to riches. The asset du jour for companies and individuals alike seems to be the amount of people following them on Twitter or fanning their Facebook page. And the faster you get those numbers up the better, means and integrity to be damned.</p>

<p>So how <em>can</em> you actively earn more followers without me looking at you in disgust? Glad you asked. It turns out there’s a book about that. The book is called <a href="http://www.cluetrain.com">The Cluetrain Manifesto</a>. It was written more than a decade ago. Yes, you read that right. Twitter wasn’t even a wrinkle in Ev Williams’s eye back then, since he was busy starting his previous venture, Blogger.com. However, even today the theses of the book are about as apt and fresh as it gets in regard to marketing yourself on Twitter.</p>

<p><em>Just like markets, Twitter is all about conversations. Write interesting content. Share interesting ideas. Post thoughtful and interesting replies to others. Point to interesting things on the web (yes, some of them can be your own posts). Iterate, rinse and repeat. Keep doing this consistently and you <strong>will</strong> find your readership flourish.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Zealand SVG Map in Black and White]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2010/02/14/new-zealand-in-black-and-white/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2010/02/14/new-zealand-in-black-and-white</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jarkko/3273520632/" title="High Tide by supervillain, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3312/3273520632_e0a3af6af4.jpg" width="500" height="151" alt="High Tide" /></a></p>
<p>We had the luxury of spending six weeks around New Zealand in last February and March, including a visit to <a href="http://www.webstock.org.nz/">Webstock &#8217;09</a>. This year&#8217;s conference is about to start within hours, and while I won&#8217;t be able to attend this time, I will celebrate the event by publishing the <span class="caps">SVG</span> New Zealand map I produced for the travelogue book of our trip (click the map to get to the <span class="caps">SVG</span> version):</p>
<p><a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/3101464/New_Zealand_location_map_bw.svg"><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20100214-cm236x5ccawk4g624ibibmkuq9.png" title="New Zealand map" alt="New Zealand map" /></a></p>
<p>The map is based on <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Zealand_location_map.svg">this map</a> on Wikipedia Commons, converted to the only true Kiwi colors, #000 and #<span class="caps">FFF</span>.</p>
<p>Since the original <span class="caps">SVG</span> file is published under the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/en:Creative_Commons">Creative Commons</a> <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 Unported</a> license, that&#8217;s what I&#8217;m going with as well. So do what you want with the map, but don&#8217;t forget the virus.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventures in Online Shopping with Shopping4net.com]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2009/10/19/adventures-in-online-shopping-with-shopping4net-com/"/>
    <updated>2009-10-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2009/10/19/adventures-in-online-shopping-with-shopping4net-com</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Update Nov 24: Turned out I indeed was too optimistic. <a href="#updates">Updated the timeline</a></strong></p>

<p>Color me lucky. I’ve done my fair share to support the online economy, but very rarely have I had experiences that have made me regret a purchase decision. I think before this summer I’ve only had to cancel or return two purchases during the decade I’ve been shopping on the internet.</p>

<p>With the aforementioned background, the first truly negative online shopping experience was even more unpleasant, courtesy of Shopping4net.com.</p>

<h3 id="july-4">July 4</h3>

<p>I order toner cartridges for my color laser and some contact lenses from Shopping4net. All items are marked to ship within 1 week in their online store. The order confirmation states July 8 as the expected shipping date. My credit card is charged immediately for the whole amount.</p>

<h3 id="july-9">July 9</h3>

<p>I receive an email saying that the shipment is delayed (without explanation) and that the new expected shipping date is July 13.</p>

<h3 id="july-14">July 14</h3>

<p>I receive another boilerplate email stating that the order is delayed, again without any explanation about the reason. This time the expected shipping date is July 17.</p>

<p>This is the last proactive communication (well, not quite, but more on that later) I receive from Shopping4net.</p>

<h3 id="august-5">August 5</h3>

<p>I’ve finally had enough and I send an angry letter to the company, where I threaten to cancel the transaction with my credit card company unless I hear more from them, soon.</p>

<p>I get a prompt response to my email where they explain that they had been waiting for the black color cartridge, but now that they checked with the distributor, that whole product is discontinued. The black toner is thus removed from the order and my credit card is credited with its price. This remains about the only thing that Shopping4net manages to handle somewhat well.</p>

<h3 id="august-10">August 10</h3>

<p>The shipment arrives—<em>without the contact lenses</em>. On top of that, the package slip is for a completely different order and client, so now I know that a guy in Western Finland ordered a Barbie overnight survival kit from Shopping4net.</p>

<p>I send another email to S4n explaining what happened.</p>

<h3 id="august-12">August 12</h3>

<p>Customer support replies to my emails and insists that the lenses were shipped within the shipment. They ask what kind of package I received and whether it seemed opened.</p>

<p>I reply with the details and tell that the package certainly seemed intact. I repeat that the invoice was addressed to a wrong client and for a wrong order.</p>

<p>I never receive a reply to my email.</p>

<h3 id="august-27">August 27</h3>

<p>I send another email to the customer support asking whether someone could even reply to my email.</p>

<p>I receive a reply the same day:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>From some reason the lenses were returned to us so it seems that our shipping staff has packed your order incorrectly and sent the lenses to a wrong client.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It <em>seems</em>? No kidding.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We will send the lenses to you again and hope they will arrive soon.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They never do.</p>

<h3 id="september-18">September 18</h3>

<p>I send yet another email asking what the status of the lenses is, given that it’s been almost <em>another</em> month and I haven’t even received a shipping confirmation.</p>

<h3 id="september-21">September 21</h3>

<p>I finally receive another correspondence from Shopping4net. They acknowledge that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>there has been a technical issue with the order and it has therefore not been sent. The issue is now fixed and the lenses shipped to you this morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A technical issue? Seriously, what the fuck?</p>

<h3 id="later-that-week">Later that week</h3>

<p>The lenses finally arrive. There is an invoice within the shipment, which I ignore since I already paid the whole order with my credit card in July.</p>

<h3 id="october-19">October 19</h3>

<p>I receive a reminder invoice from Shopping4net for the contact lenses. I send <em>yet</em> another email stating that the whole order was already paid by CC and asking them to cancel the invoice.</p>

<p>I hope the story ends here, but based on the history so far, I won’t be holding my breath.</p>

<h4 id="updates">
[Updates, November 24th]
</h4>

<h3 id="october-20">October 20</h3>

<p>Everything seems fine. I get a reply from the customer support:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hej Jarkko,</p>

  <p>Tuon korvaavan lähetyksen linssejen summa ei jostakin syystä ollut sama kuin
ensimmäisessä lähetyksessä ja summat eivät siksi ole automaattisesti
kuitannut toisia vastaan. Olemme todella pahoillamme! Olemme tietysti
poistaneet muistutuksen ja kaikki on aivan ok asiakastililläsi!</p>

  <p>Kivaa alku viikkoa sinulle!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You need to understand Finnish to appreciate the comedy in the quote. Here’s a translation, sans the broken language, of the relevant part of the message:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The sum of the replacing shipment didn’t match the original so the sums didn’t automatically cancel each other. We are terribly sorry! <strong><em>We have of course removed the reminder and everything is in order in your customer account!</em></strong> <em>(emphasis mine)</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wish it was.</p>

<h3 id="november-20th">November 20th</h3>

<p>I receive reminder invoice #2:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The following invoices from Shopping4net are past due date.</p>

  <p>We have already previously notified you that your invoices have not been paid…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Geez, is this never going to end?</p>

<p>I write another email to the customer support. Stay tuned for more…</p>

<h4 id="updates-end">[/Updates end]</h4>

<h3 id="what-should-i-and-you-have-learned-from-this">What should I (and you) have learned from this?</h3>

<p>In a nutshell, here’s Shopping4net for you based on my saga:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They don’t have a fucking clue about how to run a retail business.</li>
  <li>They lie about what items they have in stock.</li>
  <li>When your order is delayed because some item is unavailable, they will never tell you about it and after it’s delayed enough, they won’t even bother to contact you anymore.</li>
  <li>Even if the items you ordered were unavailable, they will charge your credit card right away.</li>
  <li>They will implicitly say you’re a liar unless proven otherwise.</li>
  <li>They will not respond to your support emails until you remind them several times and/or threaten them with something.</li>
  <li>They don’t have the guts to admit how they fucked up your order. Instead, they come up with ridiculous explanations like <em>technical issues</em>.</li>
  <li>When they ship backordered items, they either out of dishonesty or pure incompetence send you another invoice even if the items were part of an already paid order, which brings us back to the fact that</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Shopping4net doesn’t have a fucking clue about how to run a retail business.</strong></p>

<p>So save yourself from what we went through and order from someone else. Their cheaper prices won’t come close to making up for the shitty experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby/Rails/BDD training in Helsinki in April]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2009/02/19/ruby-rails-bdd-training-in-helsinki-in-april/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2009/02/19/ruby-rails-bdd-training-in-helsinki-in-april</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Note</strong> The actual class will be taught in Finnish</p>
<p>Two years ago we joined forces with Helsinki Polytechnic Stadia to organize a Ruby/Rails class for both students of the school and a couple of attendees from the business world. The class was a success.</p>
<p>Now we&#8217;re doing it again. The name of the school has changed to <a href="http://www.metropolia.fi/">Metropolia</a>, and the venue of the class from Arabia to Leppävaara, but the theme of the class will remain the same: teach both newbie and intermediate Ruby hackers to real wizards that can confidently write their ideas in Ruby.</p>
<p>Because of the joined effort, we are able to keep the price (like really) low, at €700 + <span class="caps">VAT</span> for the whole 4-day course. That should make the class affordable even for freelancers and individuals who&#8217;re just dabbling with Ruby and Rails.</p>
<p>There will be some differences as well. We&#8217;ll use more time to teach <span class="caps">TDD</span>/<span class="caps">BDD</span> and Ajax-related stuff, because of their increased importance lately. Most of the 4th (<span class="caps">BDD</span>) day will be taught by <a href="http://tarvainen.wordpress.com/">Antti Tarvainen</a>, a Rails and Agile wizard from <a href="http://www.leonidasoy.com/">Leonidas</a> who is also famous for his Rails workshop at the Tampere University of Technology.</p>
<p>The program of the class:</p>
<ol>
	<li><strong>Monday, April 6th</strong> Basics of Ruby, including what&#8217;s new in Ruby 1.9.</li>
	<li><strong>Tuesday, April 7th</strong> Introduction to Ruby on Rails, based on Rails 2.2.</li>
	<li><strong>Wednesday, April 8th</strong> Ajax development on Rails, Protype, script.aculo.us and accessible Ajax.</li>
	<li><strong>Thursday, April 9th</strong> Test-Driven and Behaviour-Driven Development on Rails; RSpec and Cucumber.</li>
</ol>
<p>Since alumni of our previous classes already snitched part of the spots on the class, we only have a couple places left for sale in the open. It thus pays off to be quick. As an added bonus for the fast ones, you&#8217;ll receive an extra 100€ discount if you register within a week, that is before February 26th.</p>
<p>You can register by sending email directly to <a href="mailto:jarkko@jlaine.net">me</a> .</p>
<p>Welcome to have some fun with us and challenge yourself to learn new exciting skills at the same time!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build your green home]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2008/10/04/build-your-green-home/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2008/10/04/build-your-green-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The &#8220;summer project&#8221; for <a href="http://innovatebig.com/">Rod</a>, me and <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/lorenbaxter">Loren</a>, <a href="http://ecohomeresource.com/">EcoHomeResource</a> is now live. The site is a hub of information and news for everyone wanting to build a green home or to make their current apartments more eco-friendly.</p>
<p>My dream has for quite some time (since reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/redirect.html?ie=UTF8&amp;location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2FNatural-Capitalism-Creating-Industrial-Revolution%2Fdp%2F0316353000%2F&amp;tag=jlainenet-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325">Natural Capitalism</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/redirect.html?ie=UTF8&amp;location=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2FCradle-Remaking-Way-Make-Things%2Fdp%2F0865475873%2F&amp;tag=jlainenet-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325">Cradle to Cradle</a>, to be exact) been to build us a <a href="http://www.redferret.net/?p=8707">carbon-positive home</a>, so the project has been spot-on for me.</p>
<p>The actual blog/<span class="caps">CMS</span> is using Movable Type but the backend database for products and companies is built on <a href="http://merbivore.org/">Merb</a> and <a href="http://datamapper.org/">Datamapper</a>. The integration of the platforms has definitely been a challenge but the decision to use separate pieces loosely joined by web services gives us a chance to reuse the database easily in the future if need be.</p>
<p>Playing around with new tools such as Merb, DM and jQuery (and, err&#8230; perl) has been really educational and fun. The project also gave us a chance to help hone open source products such as Datamapper even further.</p>
<p>If you&#8217;re <a href="http://ecohomeresource.com/2008/09/cooling-heating-and-insulation.html">building a new house</a>, <a href="http://ecohomeresource.com/2008/09/photovoltaic-electricity-produ.html">renovating your existing home</a>, or just looking for <a href="http://ecohomeresource.com/2008/09/how-to-light-efficiently.html">tips to be more eco-efficient with what you already got</a>, go and check out <a href="http://ecohomeresource.com/">EcoHomeResource</a>! You won&#8217;t walk out empty-handed.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
