<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | jlaine.net]]></title>
  <link href="http://jlaine.net/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jlaine.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-05T11:04:56+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jlaine.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jarkko Laine]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project 4.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://jlaine.net/2014/01/21/project-45/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-21T12:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jlaine.net/2014/01/21/project-45</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last fall – on the brink of transferring to the masters series in sports – I started a new <a href="http://projekti45.jlaine.net">triathlon project</a>. I’ve been looking for something new for a while and this seemed like a good opportunity to take it into action. I’ve also always loved triathlon. I’m a bit of a generalist in everything and always looking for variety<sup id="fnref:entrepreneur"><a href="#fn:entrepreneur" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> in everything I do.</p>

<p>The big problem in triathlon for me was that I was (and to an extent still am) a terrible swimmer. Sure, I can get by but if I tried to swim a longer distance, I quickly went out of breath, which is disturbing for someone with presumably great oxygen intake. I assume that’s very common for quite a few tri-newbs, so I also wanted to document the process as it goes.</p>

<p>Writing a sport project blog is what everyone seems to be doing right now, so I wanted to do it with a twist. I have no illusions that very many people are actually interested in me or how I’m doing. Thus I’m always trying to write articles with the audience in mind: people who have a background in endurance sports but have not done (or have recently started) triathlon.</p>

<p>For now I’m doing it in Finnish. But who knows, if the interest is there, I might start translating the articles in English as well. So, if the language isn’t an issue, come on <a href="http://projekti45.jlaine.net">over</a>.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:entrepreneur">
      <p>That’s probably why I’m a software entrepreneur rather than a pure developer. I get bored quickly when I do just one thing for too long – be it coding, designing or marketing.<a href="#fnref:entrepreneur" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
